# Joel Worrall

717.385.9970 / joel@joelworrall.com / @tangollama

## Executive Management, Strategic Leadership, Brand Development, Innovation, Technology Product Development, Digital Transformation

## Summary

I started my career in the software industry as a programmer, architect, and consultant. A decade ago, I began growing my skills in the areas of people management, organizational leadership, strategic planning, brand building, board engagement, and using technology to enable business transformation.

Today, my experiences have equipped me with a team-oriented management philosophy and strategic execution experience at multiple levels. My goal is to invest my skills and management background in both the software and international nonprofit sectors to provide senior leadership to an organization with a mission I can embrace, a culture I can influence, a team I can pour into, and a vision I can help guide.

#### Skills

- Management of departments across distributed offices, time zones, and continents
- Team leadership, mentoring staff and subordinates, managing up, and coaching peers
- Brand and product development as well as internal and external messaging
- Mass-marketing, messaging, and fundraising, including proposal creation and presentation
- Corporate strategic planning and execution with sustainable results
- Corporate culture leadership, embracing and setting pace for core values
- Personnel management, including restructuring organizational reporting relationships
- Talent identification, recruitment, and onboarding
- Volunteer recruitment and management, including open source software contributors
- Strong presentation, public speaking, and written communication skills
- A track record of creating, influencing and owning a vision for an organization
- Multi-million dollar budget management
- Nearly a decade of Board-level reporting experience

## Experience

## CURE International (since 2009)

Member of the executive leadership team, head of technology, marketing, and messaging, providing oversight and strategic direction to a global nonprofit healthcare organization with 1,500 employees and an operational presence in 29 countries.

<u>Chief Technology Officer and Office of the CEO</u> – June 2016 to present Chief Technology Officer – May 2014 to June 2016 Vice President of Technology and Marketing – July 2010 to May 2014

- Vice President of Technology October 2009 to July 2010
  - Led transition from traditional nonprofit software tools to a full cloud technology strategy
  - Served as the lead executive and primary communicator through a CEO transition

- Oversaw all technology, marketing, brand-building and creative efforts
- Co-founded the award-winning cure.org and the CUREkids real-time field reporting platform
- Co-founded the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source software project
- Wrote and spoke for conferences and events across a variety of audiences and venues
- Conducted executive recruiting and management
- Directed crisis communications and public relations
- Directed the creation of CURE's content marketing strategy
- Led the messaging, content, and execution for CURE's largest annual fundraising event (\$6M)
- Oversaw the growth of CURE's first, successful monthly recurring revenue program

Primary technologies / tools: PHP, MySQL, jQuery, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, Wordpress, Salesforce.com, Google Apps, Mailchimp, Stripe, Hubspot, DigitalOcean, Rackspace

### HospitalRun (since 2014)

Co-founder of the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source health information platform, responsible for strategic direction, community management, messaging, code contributions, and reviewing pull requests.

Core Team [Volunteer] - February 2014 to present

Primary technologies / tools: Node, Ember, CouchDB, PouchDB, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, DigitalOcean, Asure

#### Mzinga & KnowledgePlanet Inc. (3 years)

Led a 75-person engineering department of a venture-backed enterprise software company. Responsible for technology roadmap, product development, acquisition due diligence, and R&D.

Vice President, Engineering & Development – March 2009 to October 2009

<u>Director of Engineering</u> – August 2008 to March 2009

<u>Director of Development, Learning & Workplace Communities</u> – Feb. 2008 to Aug. 2008

<u>Development Manager</u> – Feb. 2007 to Feb. 2008

Software Architect – July 2006 to Jan. 2007

- Led shift of product architecture and business model from Application Service Provider to complete Software as a Service multi-tenant, single instance environment
- Provided technical leadership through a debt restructuring and recapitalization event
- Guided the engineering organization through the merger of three separate companies and development organizations as well as the incorporation of an offshore, outsourced team
- Negotiated major software vendor contracts and services
- Performed technical diligence through acquisitions
- Implemented lightweight, effective performance review and project scheduling
- Served as consultant and solution architect, working with troubled client relationships

Primary technologies / tools: Java, HTML/CSS/JS, Oracle, SVN, CVS, FogBugz

## joelworrall.com (since 2009)

Technology due diligence, early stage startup technology, marketing, and business development support.

Sole Proprietor and Senior Consultant – July 2009 to present

Sample 1: Early-stage product startup, serving as consultative CTO

- Provided product focus, technology selection, and branding direction
- Identified and recruited technology, marketing, and design talent to produce a product and a brand worthy of a national launch
- Guided brand direction, marketing and PR opportunities, and charitable aims of the corporation
- Supported the initial fundraising for the company with strategic and technical direction

#### Sample 2: Business model transformation and product due diligence

- Evaluated the business model of a national company focused on delivering rental services in entertainment settings, looking to transition to a modern, Internet business model
- Recommended and reviewed appropriate technology architectures and business processes
- Provided 1-year review and reporting to the board of directors on progress towards expected outcomes and goals

#### Java Brewery, Inc (3 years)

Outsourced system architecture, software development, and interim engineering management.

<u>Sole Proprietor and Senior Consultant</u> – April 2003 to June 2006

- Engaged in outsourced product development, management, strategic partnerships, technology, product, and market research, and executive leadership
- Provided recruiting services, partnerships, and product due diligence
- Served as technical liaison and interim managing engineer for multiple organizations seeking to build development teams, conducting training, recruitment, and technical specification assistance
- Analysis of company models, architecture, requirements, design and implementation services
- Architected the content management tools for (at the time) the 8th most trafficked property on the Internet, comcast.net

Primary technologies / tools: Java, MySQL, Postgres, CVS, SVN

### CommNav Inc. (3 years)

Lead Java developer of a 20-person startup focused on a business portal framework.

Lead Architect – July 2000 to April 2003

- Responsible for approving designs and documentation, overseeing and mentoring junior developers, and managing testing for all next-generation product development efforts
- Primary author of the development API's and system documentation

Primary technologies / tools: Java, Postgres, CVS, Bugzilla

## Education

Bachelor's in Computer Science, Messiah College, Grantham, PA (2000) Master's in Religion, Evangelical Theological Seminary, Myerstown, PA (2015)

## **Presentations & Talks**

See videos of several of my public talks and presentations at <u>joelworrall.com/talks</u>.